William R. Saunders

725 Commonwealth Ave. Boston, MA 02215 wsaund(at)bu.edu williamrsaunders.com

NASA Planetary Scientist and recent Astronomy PhD with expertise in using Earth-based stellar occultations to study the upper atmospheres of Uranus and Neptune. Additional experience in modeling planetary atmospheres and conducting observations. Extensive presentation and public speaking experience.

EMPLOYMENT Planetary Scientist

June 2024 - Present

NASA Langley Research Center, Hampton, VA Analytical Mechanics Associates (AMA), Hampton, VA Advisor: Kunio Sayangi (NASA Langley), Kirk Ayers (AMA)

Graduate Research Fellow

Sept. 2018 - May 2024

Boston University, Boston MA

Advisor: Paul Withers (BU), Michael Person (MIT)

Topics: Stellar occultations, Mars atmosphere, Uranus atmosphere

EDUCATION

Boston University, Boston, MA

Ph.D. in Astronomy Defended Feb. 2024, Graduation May 2024

NASA FINESST Fellow Advisor: Paul Withers

GPA: 3.96/4

Boston University, Boston, MA

M.A. in Astronomy May 2020

University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA

B.A. in Physics & Astronomy, summa cum laude with major honors May 2018

Advisor: Gary Bernstein Minors: Mathematics, History

GPA: 3.81/4

HONORS AND AWARDS

Best Presentation Award, International Planetary Probe Worksh	op 2024
1st Place: Poyiadjis Hospitality Innovation Competition (\$5,000)	2024
Future Investigators in NASA Earth and Space Science	and 2022-2024
Technology Fellowship (FINESST) Winner (\$100,000)	
American Geophysical Union Dewan Young Scholarship Winner	2022-2023
Massachusetts Space Grant Consortium Graduate Fellowship	May - August 2022
Massachusetts Space Grant Consortium Graduate Fellowship	Jan - May 2022
DPS Outreach and Education Grant, astro[sound]bites	2021 - 2022
AGU Sharing Science Grant, astro[sound]bites	2021
Summer Professional Development Fellowship, Boston University	May - Aug. 2021
DPS Outreach and Education Grant, astro[sound]bites	2020 - 2021
Massachusetts Space Grant Consortium Graduate Fellowship	May - Aug. 2021
Massachusetts Space Grant Consortium Graduate Fellowship	May - Aug. 2020
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Honorable Mention	April 2020
AGU Outstanding Student Presentation Award	Dec. 2019
(awarded to top 3.5%)	

Pennsylvania Space Grant Consortium Undergraduate Scholarship	2017 - 2018
University Scholar (For Advanced Undergraduate Researchers)	2015 - 2018
Dean's List	2014 - 2018
University Physics Competition Silver Medalist	Jan. 2016
National Merit Scholar (awarded to 8,000 high school seniors)	2014

TEACHING POSITIONS

Instructor of Record

July - Aug. 2022

Boston University, Boston MA AS 102: The Astronomical Universe

Teaching Fellow

Jan. 2021 - May 2021

Boston University, Boston MA AS 100: Cosmic Controversies

Teaching Fellow

Sep. 2021 - Dec. 2021

Boston University, Boston MA AS 102: The Astronomical Universe

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

First Author

- 4. Saunders, W., Person, M., Withers, P., French, R., Tubthong, C., (2024, under review). The Upper Atmosphere of Uranus from Stellar Occultations II: Revised Temperatures in the Upper Stratosphere and Lower Thermosphere. Planetary Science Journal.
- 3. Saunders, W., Person, M., Withers, P., French, R., Tubthong, C., (2023). The Upper Atmosphere of Uranus from Stellar Occultations I: Methods and Validation. Planetary Science Journal. doi.org/10.3847/PSJ/acfd27.
- Saunders, W., Person, M., Withers, P., Sayanagi, K., Young, C., Randall, C., Valle, T. (2022). Assessment of the Feasibility of Space-Based Stellar Occultation Observations of Uranus and Neptune. Planetary and Space Science. doi.org/10.1016/j.pss.2022.105431.
- Saunders, W., Person, M., Withers, P., (2021). Observations of Gravity Waves in the Middle Atmosphere of Mars. The Astronomical Journal. doi. org/10.3847/1538-3881/abf1ef.

Co-Author

- 2. Bernardinelli, P., Bernstein, G., Sako, M., Hamilton, S., Gerdes, D., Adams, F., Saunders, W., ... (2021). Testing the Isotropy of the Dark Energy Survey's Extreme Trans-Neptunian Objects. The Planetary Science Journal.
- 1. Bernardinelli, P., Bernstein G., Sako, M., Liu, T., **Saunders, W.**, ... (2020). Trans-Neptunian Objects Found in the First Four Years of the Dark Energy Survey. The Astrophysical Journal.

CONFERENCE PRESEN-TATIONS

First Author, Research

16. (Talk) Stellar Occultation Observations to Constrain

the Stratosphere of Uranus for Aerocapture
International Planetary Probe Workshop, Williamsburg, VA.

Received Best Presentation Award

15. (Poster) Revised Upper Atmospheric Temperatures and the May 2024
Need to Understand Magnetosphere-Ionosphere-Thermosphere Interactions at
Uranus
Uranus Flagship Meeting, Greenbelt, MD.

14.	(Poster) The Atmosphere of Uranus from Stellar Occultations: Revised Temperatures in the Stratosphere and Lower Thermosphere AGU Meeting, San Francisco, CA.	Dec.	2023
13.	(Dissertation talk) The Upper Atmosphere of Uranus from Stellar Occultations DPS Meeting, San Antonio, TX.	Oct.	2023
12.	(Poster) Revised Temperatures in the Upper Stratosphere and Lower Thermosphere of Uranus Uranus Flagship Meeting, Pasadena, CA.	Jul.	2023
11.	(Poster) Uranus' Lower Themosphere is Cooler than Previously Thought AGU Winter Meeting, Chicago, IL.	Dec.	2022
10.	(Oral) Uranus' Lower Themosphere is Cooler than Previously Thought NASA Outer Planets Assessment Group, Houston, TX.	Nov.	2022
9.	(Poster) Uranus Upper-Atmospheric Temperatures from Stellar Occultations EPSC meeting, Granada, Spain.	Sep.	2022
8.	(Poster) The Feasibility of Space-Based Stellar Occultation Observations of Uranus and Neptune AGU Winter Meeting, New Orleans, LA.	Dec.	2021
7.	(Invited Talk) Observations of Gravity Waves in the Middle Atmosphere of Mars AGU Winter Meeting, virtual	Dec.	2020
6.	(Talk) Measuring the Stratospheric Temperature of Uranus Using Archival Stellar Occultations AGU Winter Meeting, virtual.	Dec.	2020
5.	(Talk) Re-Analysis of the 1976 Mars Occultation of Epsilon Geminorum: Detection of Gravity (Buoyancy) Waves EPSC Meeting, virtual.	Oct.	2020
4.	(Poster) Re-Analysis of the 1976 Mars Occultation of Epsilon Geminorum AGU Winter Meeting, San Francisco, CA Winner of the Outstanding Student Presentation Award	Dec.	2019
3.	(Poster) Initial Results of a Re-Analysis of the 1976 Mars Occultation of Epsilon Geminorum Ninth International Conference on Mars, Pasadena, CA	July	2019
2.	(Poster) Impact of Ice on the Evolution of Protoplanetary Disks and Formation of Planetary Systems AAS Winter Meeting, Washington, D.C.	Jan.	2018
1.	(Talk) Optimizing Difference Imaging to Identify Trans-Neptunian Objects using the Dark Energy Survey Astrophilly Conference, Villanova, PA	Aug.	2016
Outreach			
	(Co-Convener) Listening to Our World: Sonification Applications in Research, Education, and Outreach AGU Winter Meeting, Chicago, IL.	Dec.	2022

4.	(Talk) Astro[sound]bites: A new audio resource for informal education Workshop on Astronomy Beyond the Common Senses, virtual.	Nov. 2021
3.	(Talk) Astro[sound]bites: A new audio resource for emphconveying recent astronomy research Communicating Astronomy with the Public, virtual.	May 2021
2.	(iPoster and Talk) Astro[sound]bites: A new audio resource for conveying recent astronomy research AAS Winter Meeting, virtual Conference proceeding in the Bulletin of the AAS	Jan. 2021
1.	(Talk) Astro[sound]bites: A new audio resource for conveying recent astronomy research DPS Annual Meeting, virtual.	Oct. 2020
2.	Saunders, W., Rice, M., Gagliano, A. (2022). ASTRO[SOUND]E AUDIO RESOURCE FOR INFORMAL EDUCATION. 2nd Works! tronomy Beyond the Common Senses for Accessibility and Inclusion www.astroscu.unam.mx/rmaa/RMxAC54/PDF/RMxAC54_WSaunderschaften.	hop on As- n. http://
1.	Gagliano, A., Rice, M., Saunders, W. (2021). Astro[sound]bites: a Resource for Conveying Recent Astronomy Research. ASP Confere 531, 111-117. http://aspbooks.org/publications/531/111.pdf.	
6.	Presenter and panelist: Uranus section AMA Research and Science Symposium, Hampton, VA	Aug. 2024
5.	Revised Temperatures for Uranus' Upper Stratosphere and Lower Thermosphere Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory, Laurel, MD	Nov. 2022
4.	The Shadow Chaser: A Mission Concept to Observe Uranus and Neptune Stellar Occultations NASA Langley Research Center, Hampton, VA	Jan. 2022
3.	The Shadow Chaser: A Mission Concept to Observe Uranus and Neptune Stellar Occultations Hampton Univ., Hampton, VA	Nov. 2021
2.	Impact of Ice on the Evolution of Protoplanetary Disks and Formation of Planetary Systems Meeting of the National Astrobiology Institute, NASA Ames Research Center, CA	Aug. 2017
1.	Optimizing Difference Imaging to Identify Trans-Neptunian Objects using the Dark Energy Survey (plenary talk) Yale Undergraduate Research Conference, New Haven, CT	Feb. 2017
2.	Hey, You're in the Way: Measuring Planet Atmospheres When They Align with Stars Astronomy on Tap – Lansing, MI	July 2020
1.	Hey, You're in the Way: Measuring Planet Atmospheres When They Align with Stars CAS Public Talks, Boston University, Boston, MA	May 2020

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

INVITED TALKS & COLLOQUIA

OUTREACH TALKS

OTHER EXPERIENCE

BU Meetup Co-Founder

Sep. 2022 - Present

- 1st Place: Poyiadjis Hospitality Innovation Competition, Student Wellbeing Track (2024).
- Started a program at Boston University to help graduate students meet.
- Developed and implemented code to match students into groups and maintain databases.
- Over 2000 participants in 2023-24 academic year.

SCIENCE OUTREACH

astro[sound]bites Podcast Co-Founder and Co-Host Nov. 2019 - Present

- Bi-weekly podcast companion to Astrobites.org.
- Co-hosted by Kiersten Boley, Sabrina Berger, Cormac Larkin, and me (formerly by Malena Rice and Alex Gagliano).
- Each episode features two Astrobites posts, discussion, and a "space sound".
- Available on astrosoundbites.com, Apple Podcasts, Google Play, SoundCloud, Spotify, Amazon Music, and Audible.
- Over 88 episodes and 25,000 total downloads in over 50 countries.

Brainspace Magazine Astronomy Contributor

2019 - 2022

• Brainspace is a quarterly science magazine aimed at children ages nine to fourteen with a readership of approximately 40,000.

Published Works

"It's Pi Time"	Spring 2022
"Thinking Small: The CubeSat Revolution"	Fall 2021
"Cloudy with a Chance of Bacteria"	Spring 2021
"Where did the Moon Come From?"	Fall 2020
"Bringing Home a Piece of Mars"	Winter 2019 - 2020
"Solar Storms"	Fall 2019

Astrobites Administrative Committee

2021 - 2022

- Developed the first Astrobites webinar panel event: "How to Find an Advisor" in March 2021.
- Panel attended and viewed by over 40 participants.

ComSciCon Atlanta Podcasting Expert

Feb. 2022

ComSciCon Flagship

Aug. 2021

- Flagship science communication conference for graduate students.
- Selected as attendee in 2021.

Astrobites Undergraduate Chair

2020 - 2021

- Developed the first Astrobites webinar panel event: "How to Find an Advisor" in March 2021.
- Panel attended and viewed by over 40 participants.

Astrobites Writing Contributor

2019 - 2021

- Astrobites is a graduate-student run website that summarizes recent astronomy research at an undergraduate level.
- Writers publish monthly, and peer-review others' publications.

Research Peer Advisor

2016 - 2018

- Center for Undergraduate Research and Fellowships, University of Pennsylvania
- Advise undergraduates on first steps to beginning original research.

MEDIA APPEARENCES

REACH, a Science Podcast for Kids

March 2022

APPEARENCES Recorded a segment on artificial satellites and the CubeSat revolution.

https://reach-a-space-podcast-for-kids.simplecast.com/episodes/reaching-out-what-is-a-satellite-UbxrAEyC

Guest Presenter on In Plain English podcast

Nov. 2021

Listen to In Plain English: inplainenglishpod.org.

GBH Guest Appearance

Sep. 2021

Helped explained the celestial origin of the phrase "dog days of summer" in a segment that aired on GBH. Watch the segment here: https://youtu.be/CZerMXwQJxU.

TUTORING & MENTORSHIP

Ben Connect

2020 - 2021

Mentoring two undergraduates as part of the University of Pennsylvania alumni mentorship program.

Physics Unlimited

Aug. 2020

Hosted two "facilitator sessions" for international high school students in the Physics Unlimited summer program to discuss physics and learn about academia.

Center for Undergraduate Research and Mentorship

2016 - 2018

Undergraduate Peer Research Mentor.

Dept. of Physics & Astronomy, University of Pennsylvania

2015 - 2018

Tutor for introductory physics and astronomy courses.

PROFESSIONA MEMBERSHIP

PROFESSIONAL American Astronomical Society

Division for Planetary Sciences of the AAS

American Geophysical Union

National Association of Science Writers

Sigma Xi Scientific Research Honor Society

Sonification World Chat